<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse to prove that the strongest temptations are conquerable by Christians, or, A sober defence of nature and grace against the cavils and excuses of loose inconsiderate men in a sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of London, and court of aldermen, the 14th of January, 1676/7 / by George Hickes ...</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34459</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14444585</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14444585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1060:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse to prove that the strongest temptations are conquerable by Christians, or, A sober defence of nature and grace against the cavils and excuses of loose inconsiderate men in a sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of London, and court of aldermen, the 14th of January, 1676/7 / by George Hickes ...</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid, and are to be sold by Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, X, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Temptation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102355:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE TO PROVE That the ſtrongeſt <hi>Temptations</hi> are Conquerable BY <hi>CHRISTIANS:</hi> OR, A Sober defence of NATURE and GRACE, Againſt the Cavils, and Excuſes of looſe incoſiderate Men.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preach'd before the Right Honourable the LORD MAYOR of <hi>London,</hi> and Court of ALDERMEN, The 14th of <hi>January,</hi> 1676/7.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE HICKES,</hi> B. D. Chaplain to his Grace the Lord Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> And Fellow of <hi>Linc.</hi> Coll. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I can do all things through Chriſt, that ſtrengtheneth me.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 4.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ye are of God little Childaen, and have over-come them, becauſe greater is he that is in you, than he that is in the world.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Joh. 4.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="court_order">
            <pb facs="tcp:102355:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DAVIES</hi> MAYOR.</head>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Martis xxiij. die</hi> Januarii, 1676. <hi>Anno<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Regni Regis</hi> CAROLI <hi>ſecundi,</hi> Anglie, <hi>&amp;c. xxviij.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Hicks</hi> to Print his Sermon lately Preach'd at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagstaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Jane,</hi> R. P. D.<lb/> 
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> à<lb/> Sacris dom.</signed>
               <date>Feb. 16. 1676/7.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102355:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>THOMAS DAVIES,</hi> Lord Mayor of LONDON, AND The Court of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have a ſingular veneration for your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and the <hi>Court,</hi> which makes me ſubmit my Judgment to yours, and publiſh this Diſcourſe, to comply with your joint requeſt, which I think as obliging as any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Your Authority, more than all the intereſt I have in it, will recommend it to the World, and if it be but read with as much ſatisfaction, as your Honours heard it, it will anſwer the ends of its Publication, and prove as uſeful, as it is ſuitable to the neceſſities of the age. 'Tis a ſad thing to conſider, that there ſhould be an occaſion for ſuch a Diſcourſe as this, and nothing reflects more diſhonour upon the Goſpel, or more grieves and diſhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the Miniſters thereof, then to ſee themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd by Mens extravagant Opinions, to Preach up
<pb facs="tcp:102355:3"/>thoſe Truths, they ought to preſuppoſe. But ſo, my Lord, it is, that Mens Errors and Vices give us ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for Sermons, as the ſometimes give our Law-givers matter for their Laws, and particularly <hi>Scepticiſme,</hi> which is nothing but Infidelity in ſeveral dreſſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſo poſſeſſes the Minds of Men, that inſtead of Preaching up Practical Divinity, we are often conſtrain'd to inſiſt upon Doctrinal Points. Inſtead of perſwading Men to the Love of God, we are fain now and then to prove that he <hi>is,</hi> inſtead of urging them to have a care of their Souls, we are forc'd to prove, that their Souls are <hi>beings</hi> worthy of their care, and inſtead of preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to reſiſt all manner of Temptations, and Pray for the Grace of God, we ſometimes find it needful, firſt to convince then, that they have power to reſiſt them, and that his Grace is a real thing. This bitter root of unbelief is the Reaſon, why the Goſpel hath no better ſucceſs in the World, and one of the true cauſes, why ſo many Men have a ſecret ill-will for the Ministers of it, becauſe they are an Order of Men ſet aſide to maintain the everlasting Truths of God, and oppoſe themſelves to thoſe impious Opinions, by which they are willing to Damn their Souls. But were other Men, <hi>my Lord,</hi> as Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, and underſtood their Religion as well as you, there would be no occaſions for ſuch Diſcourſes as this, but we ſhould wholly ſet our ſelves to preſs home upon Mens Conſciences the practical Duties of Religion, and by that means make the Preaching part of Divinity more
<pb facs="tcp:102355:3"/>delightful to our ſelves, and much more profitable to the Church of God. We ſhould not then complain ſo much of the unſucceſsfulneſs of our labours, <hi>but ſee more of the travel of our Souls, when the work of our Lord did proſper in our hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether we Preach Practically, or whether we Preach about Speculative Truths, we do the Work of him that ſent us; by the former, we reform Mens Vices, by the latter, we confute their Errors, by both we keep their Conſciences awake, and make it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to live without remorſe, or dye in their Sins without fear. So that the <hi>Miniſterial Function,</hi> were it meerly <hi>Humane,</hi> must needs be confeſſed to be an excellent Institution, and its greateſt Enemies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but acknowledge, that the <hi>Pulpit</hi> conduces as much as the <hi>Bench,</hi> to preſerve Civil Order, and reſtrain the exorbitant Paſſions of Men. In particular, <hi>my Lord,</hi> were it not for us, this populous City, which is now ſo happy in your Government, would be far more Wicked than it is, and both your <hi>Honour,</hi> and all other Miniſters of Criminal Juſtice, would have much more Employment for their Axes and Rods. As for you, <hi>my Lord,</hi> your <hi>Honour,</hi> by your diligent and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Adminiſtration of Juſtice hath teſtified to the World, that you bear not the Sword in vain. For ever ſince it was put into your hands, you have ſeverely Puniſhed Vice, and reform'd more diſorders, and diſorderly Perſons, than I have opportunity here to
<pb facs="tcp:102355:4"/>relate. The World ſees, and the City feels the effects of your good Government: Good Men Honour you, bad Men Fear you, God will Bleſs you, and Poſterity will mention your Name with Praiſe. In particular, none Honours your more for your private and political Virtues, than,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant,<lb/> GEORGE HICKES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102355:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 10.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There hath no Temptation taken you, but ſuch as is common to man: but God is faithful, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that you may be able to bear it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALthough the Subſtance of that Baptiſmal Oath of Allegiance, which every <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> takes at his entrance into Covenant with God, be, to renounce the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; and although this ſolemn obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be laid by God and the Church upon the Conſcience of every <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to make him more vigilant and reſolute in reſiſting the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations which the World without, the Fleſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or the Devil both ways can preſent unto him: Yet to the ſcandal both of our Nature and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, there have often been, and now are in the Church of God, a ſort of licentious perjur'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102355:5"/>
               <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who taking a pride to aggravate the weakneſs of Humane Nature, and undervalue the power of Gods aſſiſting Grace, repreſent it as impoſſible for ſinful Fleſh and Blood to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Pleaſures of ſome, and the Terrours of other Temptations; and ſo make Religion it ſelf, which is nothing, but the practice of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Pain and Pleaſure out of love to God, an idle Romantick notion, and in effect, renounce their Baptiſmal Vow.</p>
            <p>But to the lewd Pretenſions, and authority of theſe moſt inſolent Men, my Text is an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent contradiction, and reproof; wherein the Apoſtle aſſures the ſuffering <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that, as among all the ſharp Trials and Perſecutions they had undergone for Religion, none had happen'd to them, but ſuch as were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Nature of Man, or ſuch as others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them had endur'd: So for the future he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe aſſures them, that God, who was faithful to his Promiſes, would not ſuffer them to be tempted above their Strength; but upon the due exerciſe of their patience and courage in reſiſting, would make a way for them to eſcape in all their Trials, and give them ſufficient ſupplies of his Grace to ſupport and overcome the violence thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There hath no Tempation taken you,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102355:5"/>ſuch as is moderate or common to man, for God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who will not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is the true and obvious meaning of theſe words; and therefore by good analogy both of Faith and Reaſon, we may counclude, that God, who is acquainted with the infirmities of our Nature, takes the ſame care of us in all other Trials and Temptations, as the Apoſtle here aſſures us he doth in <hi>perſecutions;</hi> which are in this and many other places of the Goſpel emphatically called <hi>Temptations,</hi> becauſe that of all the Trials which men can undergo for the ſake of God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, thoſe terrible pains and ſufferings wherein perſecutions conſiſt, are by far moſt difficult to be withſtood by feeble Fleſh and Blood.</p>
            <p>But what need is there of proving ſo great a Truth by conſequence and analogy, when the promiſe of the Spirit, (that aſſiſtant form of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi>) is the moſt general promiſe of the Goſpel, and one of the principal terms upon which we are encouraged to enter into Covenant with God? For we bind our ſelves by our Sacramental Oaths, to reſiſt ſuch Temptations as unaſſiſted Humane Nature is not able to reſiſt, becauſe we are aſſur'd from the beginning to the end of the New Teſtament; <hi>That God will give his Spirit to them that ſincerely ask it, that the Graces of it are ſufficient for us, that he will perfect his Strength in Human Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102355:6"/>and <hi>that he will make us more than conquerours in all Temptations,</hi> and <hi>find out a way by which we ſhall eſcape.</hi> A conſiderable part of the Goſpel conſiſts in ſuch like promiſes of receiving ſufficient aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from God; and indeed in had been inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with his Wiſdom and Goodneſs, as he is the Author of the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> to require us to ſwear reſiſtance againſt ſuch Temptations as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Human Nature is not able to withſtand, unleſs withal ne would have given us concurrent ſupplys of ſupernatural Strength, ſufficient of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us in them, and enable us to perform what he doth exact.</p>
            <p>This then being certain, that God ſtands bound in his Goſpel to take ſpecial care to aſſiſt us in all Temptations, and grant us ſufficient ſupplys of his Grace, I proceed to prove the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequnce, That no Temptations how violent ſoever, are irreſiſtible by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or that no Temptation or Trial hath or ever ſhall happen by Gods permiſſion unto any Perſon in Covenant with him, but ſuch as is ſuitable to the Powers of Human Nature ſtrengthened by Grace, and ſuch as a reaſonable conſiderate Man that duly uſes and improves the preſent aſſiſtance of God, may not eaſily conquer and ſubdue.</p>
            <p>This aſſertion I ſhall prove two ways; Firſt, by <hi>authority</hi> or <hi>precedent;</hi> and Secondly, by <hi>reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102355:6"/>
            <p> Firſt, by <hi>authority,</hi> taken from the practice and examples of wiſe and ſober Men in all Ages, who have reſiſted the ſtrongeſt, and overcome the moſt difficult Temptations for the ſake of God; and therefore thoſe Traiterous ungodly <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who love to repreſent the cauſe of Virtue and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as deſperate and indefenſible, contradict the experiences of Ages, and belye the Records both of God and Man.</p>
            <p>I ſhall but inſtance in three or four of the moſt violent aſſur'd Temptations, which the Devils and their curſed Agents uſe as the ſtrongeſt battery to ſubdue the ſouls of the braveſt Men.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof, is the fear of <hi>Death,</hi> which <hi>Bildad</hi> in <hi>Job,</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the King of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternations, or Terrors; and yet as terrible as are the approaches of this King of Terrors, the brave adventures of thoſe gallant <hi>Heathens,</hi> who have met him with all his train of Terrors, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſtoniſhment and fear, and ſacrific'd their lives for their Country and Friends: Theſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſouls, I ſay, who could ſcarce dye for higher ends, infallibly ſhew, that 'tis ſo far from being impoſſible, that 'tis neither ſtrange, nor difficult for Reaſon without Grace, or unaſſiſted Humane Nature, to overcome the fear of Death.</p>
            <p>But then if we conſult the Records of the Church, we ſhall find the ſupreme motives of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102355:7"/>Religion to have made Cowards, and common People valiant, and the Spirit of God, which the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers call the Spirit of Might, ſo to have fortifi'd the Courage of Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; as to make them dye with more Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than the Worthies of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time would fail, as the Author to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> ſpeaks, in telling of <hi>thoſe that were ſton'd, ſawn aſunder,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Vid. imadverſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s honorabilis doctiſ. <hi>Nort. natchbulli,</hi> u. aur. in Ep.! Hebr. c. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>empaled,</hi> and <hi>ſlain with the Sword.</hi> And the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Martyrologies; the bloody Calendars of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; the Hiſtories of the Perſecutions of the <hi>Jews</hi> by the <hi>Heathens,</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by them both, and of the former and latter Reformers by the Papal <hi>See,</hi> from the time of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> to this laſt Age, are ſo many ſtanding Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents to prove, that no tryals can happen to Men, but what Humane Nature is able to bear, and particularly that Death in all his array of Terrors is no ſuch inſuperable conſideration, when it ſtands in competition with our Duty to God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniſh Chriſtians</hi> in the time of <hi>Trajan,</hi> behav'd themſelves with ſuch reſolution, and aſſurance at the <hi>Heathen</hi> Tribunals, that his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curator and their Judge <hi>Pliny</hi> miſtook their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and perſeverance for ſtubbernneſs of Opinion, or a certain Superſtitious obſtination of Mind. And afterwards in the <hi>tenth Perſecution,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102355:7"/>they ſo little regarded their Lives, that they threw them away, and offer'd unneceſſary affronts to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Gods, that ſo they might be ſure to dye <hi>Martyrs</hi> in the Fact, and have the honour to Seal the Truth with their Blood. Inſomuch that the Wiſe Council of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ex. Conſil. <hi>Elib,</hi> annv. <hi>305.</hi> ſiquas idola for gerit, &amp; ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fuerit oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſus placuit numerum eun nonre ipi Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum.</note> 
               <hi>Eliberis</hi> was fain to make a Decree to correct ſuch unwarrantable rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Zeal, and make them leſs prodigal of their Blood. But both they, and the more Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of other Countrys would have dy'd, had it been poſſible a thouſand times, rather than drop a grain of Incenſe, bow before an Idol, or do any other ſignificant Action, which Cuſtom had made a ſign of denying Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſince the corruption of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, the noble Army of reformed Martyrs in theſe <hi>Weſtern</hi> parts of the World, have choſen to meet the King of Terrors in his moſt terrible appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, I mean in the dreadful Inquiſition, and endure the moſt painful ſorts of death, rather than Worſhip a Cake of Bread, Invoke their Fellow-creatures, admit any Advocate in Heaven but Jeſus, or make the Goſpel depend upon the dictates of the <hi>Pope,</hi> how illiterate and wicked ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may be. But were there no other Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories extant but the <hi>Bible,</hi> the number of the Saints recorded there, that have embraced the moſt bitter Ignominious Deaths, and deſpiſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102355:8"/>the Torments and Shame thereof, are more than enough to prove, that there is no Temptation ſo dreadful, but what may be born by Man, and that 'tis neither impoſſible, nor ſo exceeding diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to conquer the fear of Death, as the profane and ſenſual part of the World, to the diſhonour of our Religion, pretend it to be.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inſtance, under which I ſhall bring examples to prove, that no Temptation is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible, ſhall be taken from the Sin of Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or <hi>fornication,</hi> a Sin which the World is ſo apt to excuſe, and pretend a kind of neceſſity to commit, becauſe it is ſo natural to Fleſh and Blood. And yet as natural and hereditary as the Advocates of Uncleanneſs repreſent in to be 'tis ſo far from being an irreſiſtible Temptation, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the frequent importunities of his own Lady or Miſtreſs, although beſides the quality of her Perſon, and the danger of denying, his own Youth, and all other circumſtances concurr'd to make him conſent and Yield. And were the dread of the Majeſty of the Pure and Holy God, impreſs'd upon the heart of the moſt luſtſul Satyr, but half as deep, as it was upon his, that Grace alone would be ſufficient to check his ſinful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions, and make him cry out as <hi>he</hi> did in the critical moment of Tryal, <hi>How ſhall I do this dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable act, and ſin against my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102355:8"/>
            <p> But leſt you ſhould object that <hi>Joſeph</hi> was an extraordinary perſon, and had more than common aſſiſtance from God; let us ſuppoſe the moſt ordinary unexperienc'd <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſurrounded with the ſtrongeſt Temptations imaginable, to commit this natural, and therefore concluded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquerable Sin; Let us ſuppoſe him to have the moſt charming Beauty to entice him, together with opportunity, and all other Circumſtances to heighten the Temptation, and make it as outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous as it can be imagin'd to be; yet for all this, if this Man ſhould ſay that he were not able to roſiſt this violent Temptation, he would lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Conſcience, and contradict the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal experience of the World. For if at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant God ſhould ſay unto him, as unto the <hi>Rich Man</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>Thou Fool, this night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee;</hi> That dreadful Summons to appear ſo ſoon in the next World, would make this mighty Temptation become none at all, and preſently drive out that unclean Spirit of Luſt which poſſeſt his Soul before. But much more, if at the ſame time ſhould come forth the Fingers of a Mans hand, and write upon the Wall, <hi>Mene, Mene, Tekel Upharzin,</hi> Do this, and thou ſhalt be immediately <hi>damned;</hi> I deſire any one of you to Anſwer in his heart for this Man, what you think he would do: You cannot but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102355:9"/>confeſs, that his Amorous intentions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance would be chang'd, his jovial Thoughts troubled, his Joints loos'd, and his Knees like King <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>'s, knock one againſt another. Or laſtly, let us ſuppoſe at the ſame inſtant, that an unexpected Meſſage ſhould come from his Prince, threatning the Gibbet, or the Ax, if he proceeded to gratifie his ſinful Deſires; ſuch a terrible Meſſage would undoubtedly be ſufficient to extinguiſh his preſent Flames, and reſtrain him from the Sin he intended to commit. Or not to take the advantage of ſuch frightful Enemies to his <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> as Damnation or Death, let us ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuppoſe, That a little Child, much more a Grave and Reverend Perſon, ſhould unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedly come into the Room before he proceeded to execute his filthy Luſt; certainly inſtead of finding it impoſſible to reſiſt the Damnable Sin, he would find it impoſſible for him to commit it in their prefence, unleſs he had made an utter ſhipwrack both of his Conſcience and Honour, and were become as ſhameleſs as a Beaſt. Or, let us ſuppoſe that a mighty reward, imagin a Kingdom, or ſome vaſt Sum of Money were offer'd him upon condition he would reſiſt this pretended ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible Temptation, what do you think would find Strength and Reſolution enough to overcome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102355:9"/>the unconquerable Temptation upon theſe terms, and be glad to be hired by ſuch a Reward, to abſtain from his Damnable Luſt. And therefore, if all this be true, Why ſhould not the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our own Mortality as effectually Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie our Luſts, and keep us from daring to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a preſumptuous Sin, as if God himſelf ſhould tell us we ſhould ſhortly dye? Why ſhould not the conſideration of Eternal Torments threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Goſpel, be as perſwaſive againſt Sin, as the conſideration of them written by a <hi>Spirit</hi> upon a Wall? Or why ſhould not the Meſſage of Eternal Death which we deliver from God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail as much upon Men, as the Meſſage of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Death from a King? Laſtly, why ſhould not the preſence of the Omnipreſent God over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe Men more than the preſence of a Man? Or, why ſhould not the Infallible Promiſe of Heaven and Infinite Happineſs, be a more powerful motive to Self-denyal, than the Promiſe of a Kingdom, or Treaſure here below?</p>
            <p>The ſhameful inconſideration, ſtupidity, and carnality of Mens hearts, is the cauſe why Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral expectations and propoſals have more force upon their Souls, than the hopes of Eternal Glory; and that preſent or approaching ſenſible Pain or Loſs, fills their earthy Minds with more dreadful apprehenſions, than the proſpect of Infinite Miſery to come.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102355:10"/>
            <p> But to conclude this Inſtance with a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Argument; If the Temptations to this Sin be ſo very difficult to be reſiſted, as Debauch'd Men pretend it is, how comes it to paſs, that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Religious Parents ſuffer their Children to Sojorn in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and dwell in the Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> I mean to go abroad and converſe in this wicked World? How dare they expoſe their Souls, which they tender next to their own, to ſuch certain dangers in an Adulterous Generation, if to deny ones ſelf, and reſiſt the Temptations of the <hi>Fleſh</hi> be either impoſſible, or next to impoſſible, as the injurious Diſcourſes of the unclean Spirits of this licencious Age upon all occaſions repreſent it to be?</p>
            <p>My third Inſtance to prove how capable the nature of Man, by Gods Grace, is to reſiſt or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the moſt dangerous Temptations, ſhall be taken from a Temptation to commit ſome Sin upon a certain propoſal of gaining or looſing a <hi>Crown.</hi> Among all the Trials or Temptations the World, the Devil, or our own Hearts can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto us, none can be more powerful or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquetable than this: For a Crown is the higheſt ſecular Intereſt, the poſſeſſion of it is both Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Riches, and by conſequence, the hopes of getting, or fear of looſing that ſupreme degree of Temporal Happineſs, which conſiſts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102355:10"/>in the enjoyment of it, muſt at leaſt to covetous, or ambitious Souls, be the ſtrongeſt inducement that can be to Sin. And yet as powerful as this motive is, <hi>Moſes,</hi> who might have paſſed for the Son of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter, and by conſequence, have been Heir preſumptive to his Crown, when he came to Years, (as the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writes) rather than renounce the Covenant, which his Anceſtors made with God, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate himſelf from his viſible Church, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fake his Brethren, though the perſecuted People of God, refuſed to be call'd, that is, to be the Son of that Auguſt Princeſs, and expect the moſt glorious Kingdom of the World. And not to ranſack forreign Hiſtories, or multiply Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in this ſhort Diſcourſe, our late Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, whom God was pleaſed to make perfect through ſufferings, and reſerve for theſe latter times, as the moſt glorious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Courage that ever was in the World. That incomparable Prince and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> rather than Rob God, Proſtitute his Royal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, juſtifie Sacrilege and Rebellion by Law, and Perjure his Righteous Soul, by accepting thoſe Sinful Conditions the Rebels propoſed; after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other unparallell'd ſufferings, choſe to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice his Blood to his Conſcience, and ſecure his Innocence by the loſs of his Triple Crown.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102355:11"/>
            <p> My laſt Inſtance to prove how capable Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is to reſiſt Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall be taken from the natural deſire of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi> which of all other ſinful affections, but Pride and Self-love, from whence it proceeds, diſcovers it ſelf early in Man: For with how much impatience and eagerneſs will even little Children ſtrive to be revenged? How quickly will they reſent, and how long remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber injuries; and how will Malice, as it were, poſſeſs their little Souls; and Anger, the actual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Malice, ſwell their Hearts and Eyes? And how natural this Sin is to the corrupt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Man, and how proper it is to ſome particular complexions and tempers; the <hi>Brawls, Curſes, Duels, Factions, Slanders, Libels, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Schiſms,</hi> and <hi>Rebellions,</hi> which happen in all Societies of Men, are moſt ſad deplorable proofs. And yet if any Man deny that it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to mortifie this damnable paſſion of Revenge, wherein the Image of the Devil ſo much conſiſts, he Libels the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, and injures the Reputation and Authority of the Goſpel, which teacheth Men to <hi>forgive and love their enemies,</hi> to <hi>bleſs them that curſe us,</hi> and <hi>to do good to them that hate us and deſpite fully uſe us.</hi> This Doctrin is proper to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> above all the Religions in the World; God hath made it the very condition upon which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102355:11"/>he'l accept our Oblations, and grant us Pardon for our Sins; and <hi>therefore if thou bring by gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy Brother hath ought againſt thee, leave thy Gift there, and go thy way, thou muſt firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then return, and offer thy gift.</hi> And unleſs we can prevail with our ſelves to <hi>forgive men their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes,</hi> the Oracle of our Religion hath aſſur'd us, 'tis in vain to Pray for the Pardon of our own. Therefore if it be impoſſible to reſiſt Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to this deviliſh Sin of Revenge; or which is all one, to Forgive the Enemy that ſtrike the firſt ſtroke, 'tis impoſſible to be Saved, or elſe all the Precepts of mutual forbearance and forgiving one another muſt paſs for Goſpel-gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, or only for the Romantick and Ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal part of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us not at all to practice or believe. But alaſs, 'tis as eaſie to conquer this damnable Paſſion of Revenge, as to become Meek, and Humble, and Charitable; for the mutual exerciſe of which moſt excellent Graces, the Primitive <hi>Christians,</hi> as <hi>Marcellinus</hi> hath obſerved, were famous among the <hi>Heathens,</hi> when Slanders, Quarrels, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and all other Tragical effects of <hi>Revenge,</hi> were ſcarce ever heard of in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>But beſides the Examples I have taken out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102355:12"/>the Bible, and other Sacred Hiſtories to prove under theſe four Inſtances, that no Temptations are too ſtrong to be overcome, let me add ſome examples out of <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Hiſtorians for the further confirmation of this fundamental Truth.</p>
            <p>Under my firſt Inſtance I might have produc'd a thouſand illuſtrious Examples, as of <hi>Socrates, Regulus, Curtius;</hi> all which choſe to dye very cruel Deaths: The firſt, rather than deny God; The ſecond, rather than perjure his Soul; And the third, to deliver his Country from a Plague.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Inſtance I might have adorn'd with the memorable examples of <hi>Scipio Numantinus,</hi> and <hi>Mahumet</hi> the Great; whereof the firſt abhor'd to look upon that charming Beauty which his Captains preſented unto him, as his prize: And the latter, after an humble remonſtrance of his Lords, how much it was beneath the Majeſty of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperour to enſlave it ſelf to the Weaker Sex, immediately ſacrificed his deareſt <hi>Miſtreſs Irene</hi> to his Honour, with his own victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Hands. The Action was Barbarous, but the Self-denial was great, and may juſtly ſerve to upbraid thoſe ſlothful cowardly <hi>Christians,</hi> who have not only loſt all ſenſe of Honour, but all ſenſe and conſideration of infinite future Rewards, and ſo harden their hearts, that they will not attend to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102355:12"/>the dictates of their own Reaſon, and thereby diſpoſe their Souls to hearken to the ſecret Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and Inſpirations of God. They could be content to have him for their Champion, but not for their Second; for they hate to aſſiſt him, or which is all one, to let him aſſiſt them againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; but becauſe they cannot do all, therefore they will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor contribute that little they have left as men, to ſecure themſelves from Sin. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, they will not, like <hi>Cornelius,</hi> prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Morality for Grace, but would have God entirely force their Nature, and influence their Souls by the irreſiſtible motions of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; being unwilling to do ſo much in Spiritual Matters, as is requiſit to denominate good Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons their own.</p>
            <p>Under the third Inſtance I might have added the great Examples of <hi>Abdolominus, Diocleſian,</hi> and <hi>Otho;</hi> the firſt of which was unwilling to change a private Life for a Crown; The ſecond chang'd, a Crown, I cannot ſay, but the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> which had <hi>Crowned heads for Subjects,</hi> for a private Life; And the third, though he was elected Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour by his conquering Legions, refus'd to ratifie the Election by his Sword, but Kill'd himſelf, on purpoſe to leave the Imperial Seat to his Rival, and ſave the expence of his faithful Souldiers Blood.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102355:13"/>
            <p> The fourth Inſtance I might have confirm'd with the Teſtimony of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, all which determin with one Voice, that Revenge is a Paſſion violent in none, but weak and cowardly Souls; and that Revenge an injury, as the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> imports, is according to the Doctrin of <hi>Maximus Tyrius,</hi> to offer one again; ſo that he that Returns is as much to be condemned by the Verdict of right Reaſon, as he that gives an Affront.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſince 'tis plain by theſe Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that bare Reaſon and <hi>Moral Gallantry</hi> of Spirit, have ſometimes enabled <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Mahumet ans</hi> to reſiſt thoſe <hi>Pains,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts,</hi> which, as all men grant, are the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Temptations to Sin; is it not ſhameful Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, and horrid Impiety for <hi>Christians,</hi> whom God, without a juſt provocation, never fails to ſupport and aſſiſt with his Grace, to magnifie the weakneſs of Humane Nature, and the ſtrength of theſe and the like Temptations, with a Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious deſign, nor only to juſtifie themſelves and excuſe others, but to Debauch Mankind to the utmoſt of their power, and render the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the moſt grievous intollerable Religion that ever was in the World?</p>
            <p>From whence I proceed to prove by Reaſon that no Trial or Temptation can happen to Men,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102355:13"/>but ſuch as is ſuitable to Humane Nature, aided with Grace, and ſuch as any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that is true to his own endeavours, and faithfully uſes the reſtraining and aſſiſting helps of God, my not eaſily conquer and ſubdue.</p>
            <p>My firſt Reaſon ſhall be taken from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the nature of <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> which are nothing, but an habitual power, and ability in the Rational Soul of Man, to bear all ſenſible Pain and Loſs, and forbear all ſenſible Pleaſure and Profit, out of love to Reaſon and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Laws of God. This excellent ſpiritual power and ability of the Soul, as far as it is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, or acquired by our own Acts and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, is of Moral conſideration, but as it is ſupernaturally wrought in the Soul, or infus'd into it by the Spirit of God, ſo far it is of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical conſideration, and belongs not to Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, but Divines. But becauſe Grace, as all Men grant, is the perfection of Nature, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Virtue is conſiſtent with infus'd; I have put them both together in one Definition, in which Divines and Philoſophers both agree. But were it impoſſible, or ſo exceeding difficult as ſome Men make it, to reſiſt Temptations; this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Grace or Virtue would be but an uſeleſs fictitious notion, and Divines and Philoſophers from the beginning of the World would have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102355:14"/>been either Knaves or Fools. All the excellent Sermons the former have made with ſo much elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and authority concerning <hi>Mortification, Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial,</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> and all the brave Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes the latter have penn'd with ſuch admirable Reaſon and Rhetorick, concerning <hi>Fortitude, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> are idle unprofitable Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangues, and as inſignificant to the impotent Race and Nature of Man, as the practical Rules of Dancing to a Cripple, or a Lecture in <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry</hi> to a natural Fool. In particular, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who Magnifies the Grace of God ſo much in his Epiſtles, and proteſts he took pleaſure in bearing <hi>Reproaches, Perſecutions,</hi> and <hi>Diſtreſſes</hi> for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake. This great Doctor and Saint, who declar'd upon his own experience, that he was alwaies moſt ſtrong, when he was moſt weak, and that he could do and ſuffer all things through the ſtrength he receiv'd from Chriſt, muſt paſs for a Cheat, or Enthuſiaſt, if Men by the promiſed ſupports and aſſiſtance of Gods Grace be not able to reſiſt Temptations unto Sin.</p>
            <p>There was never yet in the Church of God a more apt Example to confirm this Doctrin I now maintain, than this Apoſtle was; for when the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> perſecuted his righteous Soul with ſo much rage and violence as to make him call them the <hi>Meſſengers of Satan,</hi> and compare
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102355:14"/>the ſharpneſs of the Perſecution, which they rais'd againſt him, to a <hi>thorn in the fleſh;</hi> like a true Souldier of Chriſt, he ſtill reſiſted and held out; but yet ſuſpecting his own perſeverance, and fearing leſt his Faith and Patience might at laſt fail, he <hi>Prayed God thrice</hi> to remove the ſharp Trials from him: But God, who knew whereof he was made, better than he himſelf, ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd them, aſſuring the ſuffering Apoſtle, that <hi>his concurrent Grace was ſufficient for him, and that his ſtrength was made perfect in his weakneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This relation the Apoſtle makes of himſelf, is either true or falſe: If falſe, then he was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> or a <hi>Mad-man:</hi> If he was Mad, as the <hi>Feſtuſes</hi> of this Age repreſent him to be, how came he to ſpeak the words of Truth and Soberneſs? Hw came he to write ſuch learned and profound Epiſtles, and make ſuch admirable defences for himſelf and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, before ſo many Procurators, and the Emperour himſelf at <hi>Rome?</hi> How came he to be ſo very Wiſe upon occaſion, as to plead the Priviledge of a <hi>Roman</hi> Citizen, and divide the <hi>Sadducees</hi> againſt the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when they had both conſpir'd to take away his Life? How came he to baffle the <hi>Jews</hi> out of their own Traditions and Prophecies, to convert the greateſt Cities of the World to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, and acquire ſuch a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102355:15"/>Veneration and Authority, not only among the common People, but among the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers both of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome?</hi> To conclude, how came the Church Univerſal to Canonize his Writings; and how came they particularly to be ador'd by ſuch gallant Men as <hi>Juſtin, Origen, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> and <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who were all as great Wits and Philoſophers as ever the World could ſhew.</p>
            <p>An Impoſtor likewiſe he could not be; for then he muſt have acted for Glory, or Gain. For Glory he did not; becauſe he hath ſo often ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd his own Sinfulneſs, Unworthineſs, and Inſufficiency, repreſenting himſelf as the <hi>leaſt of the Apoſtles,</hi> and freely confeſſing that he was what he was by the Grace and deſignation of God. And for Gain or ſecular Intereſt he could not act, for in this Life, he was of all Men moſt miſerable; his Apoſtolical Office rendring his whole Life but a continual Tragedy or Catalogue of Miſeries; as you may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. from the 23. to the end of the Chapter. This Story, then, I cited out of his Writings muſt be infallibly true; and if it be, then Virtue and Grace are <hi>real notions;</hi> and by conſequence, no Tempation can happen to any Man, but what Humane Nature is able to bear. And leſt you ſhould think that God had a more particular care for this Apoſtle than other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102355:15"/>
               <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and ſupply'd him with more particular aids, than the reſt of the Church, you may find him exhorting the whole Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to be <hi>strong in the Lord and the power of his might;</hi> you may find him charging <hi>Timothy</hi> to be ſtrong in <hi>the grace that is in Christ;</hi> and exhorting the whole City of the <hi>Philippians,</hi> to work out their Salvation with care and ſollicitude, becauſe God, by his preventing and aſſiſting Grace was working in their hearts both to Will and to Do. <hi>Perſeverance</hi> or <hi>the working out of Salvation,</hi> conſiſts in nothing but in conſtantly reſiſting Temptations to Sin; and there can be no ſenſe in that, nor any other ſuch like Exhortations, unleſs God (as the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist</hi> ſpeaks) be a preſent help in time of trouble, and his aſſiſting Grace concur to the aid and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of all thoſe that need, and ſincerely deſire it; and, like the good and faithful Servant in the Goſpel, improve it as faſt as it is beſtowed.</p>
            <p>To all which let me add the Precepts of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, Patience, and Self-denial; the Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to keep our ſelves <hi>Pure, Temperate, Sober, Chaſt,</hi> to be <hi>ſtedfast</hi> and <hi>unmoveable,</hi> to be <hi>ſtedfaſt to the end,</hi> to <hi>reſist the Devil,</hi> to <hi>reſist him unto Blood:</hi> Of all which and the like Exhortations, if we conſider God as the Original Author, it muſt needs follow, that Men in Covenant with him, have ordinarily power to reſiſt the World, the Fleſh,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102355:16"/>and the Devil, nay to reſiſt them all to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to Blood. And therefore none but <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> can be ſo abſurd and impious as to imagin that God (with Reverence be it ſpoken) can ſo tranſgreſs the Rules of common ſenſe, as to adviſe his Creatures to the practice of thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which he knew bofore were impoſſible to be done. Nay this damnable aſſertion of the <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> of this Age, (who, like that filthy Goat <hi>Nero,</hi> think all the World as laſcivious as themſelves,) robs God of his Goodneſs, by imagining he can delude his reaſonable Creatures ſo far, as to put them upon the Practice of thoſe Duties, which he knew were impracticable and above their Power to do. But God, that is better acquainted with our Nature than we our ſelves, can put us upon nothing, but what he knows is either abſolutely in our power, or at leaſt, as to conquer Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is, within the power of our Nature, aſſiſted by Grace to perform. For this very reaſon it is, that God and the Church bind every <hi>Christian</hi> at his firſt admiſſion into Covenant by ſuch a ſolemn Oath to reſiſt Temptations, as I mention'd in the beginning of this Diſcourſe: the ſubſtance of which ſolemn obligation amounts to thus much; I do here in the preſence of God, my Saviour, and all the Heavenly Hoſt devote my ſelf to the ſervice of God; I call Heaven, and Earth, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102355:16"/>Church Militant and Triumphant to bear witneſs that I renounce the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; and that I'le reſiſt their Temptations to my laſt breath. This I avow to be my reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and upon this condition, and this alone, I now deſire to enter into Covenant with my God, and be admitted into his Church; and I call my Conſcience to Record this day, that I will never repent of this Promiſe, nor revoke it, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue Chriſts faithful Souldier to the end of my Life: So help me, O my God. 'Tis impoſſible for the Conſcience of Man, or Angel to be bound by a ſtronger Obligation than this; but unleſs the Matter of it be practicable, 'tis a ſolemn piece of Nonſenſe and Deluſion; and God and his Church for above 1600 Years have mock'd and abus'd the World.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon, by which I undertake to prove my Aſſertion, ſhall be taken from the conſideration of the nature of <hi>Repentance;</hi> which conſiſts in an unfeigned ſorrow for our Sins paſt, and a ſincere Reſolution by Gods aſſiſtance to lead an Holy Life for the time to come. But if Men be conſcious to themſelves, that the Sins they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted they could by no means reſiſt, why ſhould they ſorrow and repent for what is paſt, or ſo contradict themſelves, and mock God, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe amendment for the time to come? Why
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102355:17"/>inſtead of confeſſing their Sins to him, do they not rather expoſtulate with him, and ſay, 'Tis true, O Lord, I have done many things which Men that pretend to be thy Miniſters, and trouble the World by thy Authority, declare to be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sins; but if they be, I proteſt I could not help it; Thou knoweſt I could not reſiſt them; and if Thou wouldſt have me do better for the time to come, thou muſt give me more Grace than hitherto I have had. Which horrible Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulation ſhews how inconſiſtent this damnable Doctrin I oppoſe, is to the Duty of Repentance; how ridiculous it renders Confeſſion and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Sin; nay how it makes the greateſt Sins we are tempted to commit no Sins at all: And many more ſuch dreadful conſequences flow from it, as may juſtly make the <hi>Blades</hi> or licentious Wits, that talk it about the Town, if they have any Senſe or Conſcience left, to abhor it, and recant.</p>
            <p>My third Reaſon is taken from the conſideration of the Nature of Laws; which commonly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the things they command, or forbid, contain either general or ſpecial Threatnings and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as moſt proper and ſuitable motives to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to perform the Duties we ought to do, and abſtain from the Sins we ought not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: But if the free and rational Nature of Man,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102355:17"/>neither ſimply in it ſelf, nor with the aſſiſtance of God; if Reaſon with, no more than without Grace, have power to overcome Temptations to wilful Sin, it would be tranſcendent Folly and Cruelty for Princes, and States to make Temporal Laws for their Subjects; and much more for God to make Spiritual Laws for his Church. He might with as much Wiſdom and Juſtice have charged Men not to be Hungry, or Sick; not to be Hot, or Cold; as not to commit Adultery, not to Steal, not to Murther, not to bear Falſe Witneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſs by ſome means or other it be in their power to reſiſt the ſtrongeſt Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that the Wit of Men or Devils can invent, to induce them to commit the foreſaid Sins.</p>
            <p>My fourth Reaſon I ground on the <hi>10th</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew, v.</hi> 33. where our Saviour declares that Whoſoever ſhall deny him before Men, that him will he deny before his Father whith is in Heaven: But were any Suffering ſo intolerably ſharp, were any perſecutions ſo diſmal and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, that it were impoſſible for ſupported Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature to bear them; were all the Torments of a <hi>Roman</hi> Inquiſition, and all the Artifices of Cruelty, which Wit and Malice could invent, above the Courage and Reſolution of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and inſuperable by Reaſon, ſtrengthened with Grace: The Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who took our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102355:18"/>upon him, and knew by experience what Humane Nature was: He, I ſay, that was made like unto his Brethren, that he might be a Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Faithful High-Prieſt, would never deny any Man a ſhare in his Atonement, for doing that, which extremity of Torment muſt force him to commit.</p>
            <p>To conclude with ſuch another Reaſon: You may remember that our Saviour, in the Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption he gives of Hell, in the 9th of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> hath this ingenious <hi>Hebrew</hi> Phraſe, <hi>Where their Worm dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not;</hi> which <hi>Worm,</hi> according to the ſenſe both of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here; and in the 66th of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> but that Stinging remorſe of Conſcience, or continual Fret, or Vexation of Soul in Damned Spirits, cauſed by the remembrance, and conſideration of the wilfull. Treachery and Baſeneſs of their own Hearts, in committing thoſe Sins, and yielding to thoſe Temptations, which they knew they had power ſufficient to reſiſt. But were the Damn'd Souls in Hell of this opinion, that it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, or next to impoſſible, for Men to reſiſt Temptations; were they conſcious to themſelves that they were overcome by all Temptations to which they yielded, becauſe they wanted power ſufficient to conquer them; what outward Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſoever they may endure, they muſt needs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102355:18"/>be free from inward Pangs and Torments, from that intolerable horror and remorſe of Conſcience which our Saviour calls the <hi>Worm,</hi> becauſe, like a <hi>Moth</hi> or <hi>Worm,</hi> it conſtantly frets and gnaws upon the tendereſt part of the Soul that breeds it, and increaſes the Torments of Hell more, than all the Rivers of Fire and Brimſtone that conſtantly flow therein.</p>
            <p>And thus, I hope, I have ſaid enough to confirm and illuſtrate this great Truth, having prov'd it both by <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and charg'd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary error (or Blaſpemy ſhall I ſay) with ſuch abſur'd and damnable Conſequences, as may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make any Man, that is not deſperate, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd and afraid to aſſert it in the preſence of God, and reaſonable Men. But we live (<hi>God knows</hi>) in a Nation and Age, wherein Sin and Nonſenſe are Preſumptuous, and wherein 'tis long ſince become faſhionable and gentile to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion Principles, and deny all thoſe fundamental Truths of natural and revealed Divinity, which neither <hi>Heathens</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ever Queſtioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This is the reaſon, why Divines, whom God hath ſet for the ſervice and defence of the Goſpel, have of late been fain to lay the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations again, and Preach up ſuch Doctrins as ſober Men, not acquainted enough with the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Time, have judged at firſt hearing,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102355:19"/>to need no proof: Such as the <hi>being and providence of God, the immortality of the Soul,</hi> and <hi>the neceſſity of good works;</hi> to which I may add the Subject of this Diſcourſe, which hath been to prove, that no Temptations which God ſuffers to fall upon <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are irreſiſtible, or that no thinking, circumſpect, vigilant Man, that's true to his own Reaſon, and careful to make uſe of the promiſed aſſiſtance of God, can be over-matched by any Trial, though never ſo ſharp, nor meet with any Temptation too ſtrong to be withſtood, how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful or charming ſoever it be.</p>
            <p>And this Doctrin being proved by ſo many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable <hi>experiments,</hi> and <hi>reaſons,</hi> I hope may be ſufficient to demonſtrate the Folly, and chaſtiſe the Inſolence and Impiety of thoſe Prophane Men, who, becauſe they have enſlaved themſelves to their own Paſſions, affect to make Man like a Beaſt, (that is, like themſelves) all Senſe and Appetite, and repreſent him as determin'd in all his actions by outward objects, and unable to moderate his Luſts, and Fears. But had theſe Men but common Reverence for God, or man, they would not ſo Libel the Nature of the latter, which is the workmanſhip of the former; they would be more modeſt and civil, than to define Humane Nature by their own Corruptions, or pretend to judge of the Thoughts, Actions, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102355:19"/>Inclinations of all other Men by their own; they would be more conſiderate and reſerv'd, and not take a Pride to maintain and propagate an Opinion which is chargeable with ſuch foul and abſurd concluſions, and which ſhews them to be an inconſiderate ſort of Men, that Think little, and Talk much, and makes them obnoxious to that dreadful curſe pronounced by the Prophet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe, that <hi>call good evil, and evil good; that put light for darkneſs, and darkneſs for light; that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twould be very ſeaſonable for theſe Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Times, that ſuch Blaſphemers Tongues were reſtrained by ſevere Laws, that they might only diſcourſe theſe, and their other pernicious Doctrins in their own <hi>Cabals,</hi> and not dare to divulge them, and corrupt and trouble the company of civil, and ſober Men, wich ſuch damnable confident talk. But ſince theſe Mens Tongues are their own, and in this great defect of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, they take the liberty to ſpeak of God and Man as they pleaſe, 'tis more neceſſary that they ſhould be rebuk'd, and their horrid Opinions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd and confuted in the Pulpit, leſt their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Doctrin ſhould ſpread, and corrupt the World like a Canker, while the Miniſters of the Goſpel hold their Peace.</p>
            <p>As for this Opinion, it deveſts Man, as you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102355:20"/>have heard, of his better part, <hi>viz.</hi> his free and rational Nature, wherein the Image of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts; it proves all Laws and Orders of Societies to be uſeleſs, inſignificant, and unnatural Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and ſo makes the Legiſlative Power, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inveſted in God, or the King, to be Tyranny and Violence; and Men that live under Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be worſe Slaves, than the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>AEgypt,</hi> where they were commanded to make <hi>Brick, when they had no Straw.</hi> It contradicts the Doctrinal and Hiſtorical parts of Scripture, and with unparallel'd Impudence, gives the Lye to the <hi>Martyrologies</hi> both of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. It contradicts the Definition of Virtue and Grace; in particular, it makes <hi>Fortitude, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Self-denial, Patience, Sobriety, Chaſtity,</hi> and all other infus'd and acquir'd Habits of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Sin, to be idle Fictitious notions; and ſo makes all the Divines and Philoſophers that have ever been, to have been Impoſtors or Fools. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, it is inconſiſtent with the Doctrin of Repentance, and deſtroys the Goodneſs and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, who, upon the ſuppoſition that the Scriptures are true, hath exhorted his People to the practice of ſuch Duties, which he knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they could not do. To conclude, it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws the Catholick Hypotheſis of aſſiſting Grace, diſſolves the Obligation of our Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102355:20"/>Vows, diſarms Hell of the moſt exquiſit part of its Torments, and confounds the notion of Good and Evil, by making it Lawful, in ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it ſometimes neceſſary for Men to commit the moſt heinous Sins. All which abſurd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Conſequences, I hope, you now hear with <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Indignation, and will remember here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after with horrour and diſdain, when ever you ſhall hear theſe ſenſual Men, like thoſe that were ſent to ſpy out the Holy Land, repreſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Brethren, as <hi>Graſhoppers;</hi> but their Spiritual Adverſaries, the Temptors and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations with which they ought to conflict, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable <hi>Anakims,</hi> as enemies of a prodigious ſtature, greater, and taller, and ſtronger than themſelves. But theſe are uſually Men, that have <hi>turn'd the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, whoſe glory is their ſhame, whoſe God is their belly, who mind earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things.</hi> And becauſe they have debauch'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Brute Beaſts, or at leaſt have a mind to do ſo, therefore (as St. <hi>Jude</hi> Speaks) they <hi>foam out their ſhame</hi> and infidelity in ſlandering the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal nature of Man, exploding the Doctrin of aſſiſting Grace, Drolling upon Godly Men, and diſcrediting, as much as they can, the Authority of the Goſpel, becauſe it thwarts their Luſts, and diſturbs their ſenſual repoſe, by Teaching, that Men by the grace of God have power to
<pb facs="tcp:102355:21"/>
               <hi>overcome the World, reſiſt the Devil,</hi> and <hi>deny all ungodlineſs and wordly Luſts;</hi> and becauſe it exhorts Men in Gods name to be <hi>patient, vigilant,</hi> and <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt;</hi> to be <hi>ſober, temperate,</hi> and <hi>chast;</hi> to <hi>fight the good fight;</hi> to <hi>finiſh the courſe;</hi> and <hi>perſevere unto the end.</hi> Laſtly, becauſe it aſſures us that God aſſiſts us in all our Spiritual Combats, ſupports us in all our Trials, and will make us more than Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours through Chriſt that loveth us; nay, <hi>that Chriſt himſelf, who hath ſuffered and been tempted, is able to ſuccour them that are tempted;</hi> and that no Temptation hath taken us, but ſuch as is mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and common to Man; becauſe God is faithful to his Promiſes, and will not ſuffer us to be Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted above our ſtrength, but will with the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation make a gracious way to eſcape, that we may be able to bear it.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Letter to a Deiſt,</hi> in Anſwer to ſeveral Objections againſt the Truth and Authority of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> Sold by <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Yard.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102355:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
